# Curriculum Vitae

## Garima Singh

Assistant Professor, School of Journalism and Mass Communication Address: Himgiri Zee University, P.O. Sherpur, Chakarata Rd, Dehradun, Uttarakhand. 248197 (India)

#### Email Id:

ahluwalia.garimasingh@gmail. com

**Phone No:** (+91) 8477012743

Proactive lecturer and researcher with 9+ years' experience of teaching graduate and post graduate students. Supervising 3 PhD research scholars, guided 6 MA and 20+ BA dissertations. Reviewed 3 chapters for the Proposed Book on "Gender, Place, and Identity of South Asian Women by IGI Global Publisher. Listed as young peer-reviewer with Journal of Gender Studies.

#### ORCID ID:

https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4021-8939

-Presented research paper titled "Degrees of Subjectivity: Humane approach to social science research and data" in the Virtual Global Conference, ICMC 2022, organised by MICA, India, in collaboration with University of Southampton, England. (5-7 January, 2022)

### **Education:**

2018 - Ph.D. in Media and Communication Studies from Doon

University, Uttarakhand (India)

2012 - M.A. in Communication from Doon University,

Uttarakhand, India (With a CGPA of 8.72)

2009 - B.A. from D.A.V. PG College, H.N.B.G. Central

University, Uttarakhand, India (With 63 %)

# **Professional Appointments:**

Since 2018 - Till Date Assistant Professor,

School of Journalism & Mass

Communication,

Himgiri Zee University, U.K., India

### PhD - Course Work and Supervision

 Guiding and Co-guiding Research Scholars

# Courses Taught – Post Graduate and Graduate students

- Film Studies/Appreciation
- Communication Research
- Cultural and Political Studies
- Visual Communication

### Services Offered:

- Served as **Guide/Supervisor** for Bachelors and Masters Students' *Dissertation* work.
- Conducted **Weekly Film Screenings** for Film Studies' students.
- Class sessions with **Vocational Courses** on semester basis

2015 – 2018 Guest/Visiting Faculty School of Media, Journalism and Communication & School of Management,

Himgiri Zee University, U.K., India

In this capacity I was responsible for taking lectures on hourly basis. I took various subjects including Research, Film Studies, Economic Development and Planning, etc.

- Published chapter in **IGI Global publisher's** book **"Gender, Place, and Identity of South Asian Women"**(https://doi.org/10.4018/97

8-1-6684-3626-4.ch008).

- Reviewed three chapters for the IGI Global publisher's book "Gender, Place, and Identity of South Asian Women".

- Recently published article "Sanjay Leela Bhansali and the Female Gaze" with the Online Journal "The Female Gaze" https://thefemalegaze.org/2021/12/01/sanjay-leela-bhansali-and-the-femalegaze/
- Ongoing Projects: Parked research paper titled "Colonial countering of Azad Hind Radio: A critical analysis of George Orwell's BBC Broadcasts" with the Journal Communicator, IIMC, New Delhi, India (Peer-Reviewed Journal)
- Reviewed two research papers for **The Journal of Communication and Media Studies,** Common Ground Research Networks, University of Illinois Research Park, USA (2021 & 2022).

Listed as Young Peer Reviewer – Journal of Gender Studies (Scopus Indexed) (July 2022)

2012-2014

Lecturer, Department of Journalism and Mass Communication,

BFIT Group of Institutions, U.K., India

### Courses taught – Graduate Students

- Writing for Mass Media
- Mass Media and Society
- Photojournalism

#### Services Offered

- Managed student fests and events
- Worked with institute's house journal "Happening" as content creator.

## **Publications:**

## Articles/Papers:

Short research article titled "Individual as the 'Other': A Lacanian reading of Digital Public Sphere" by

Academia.Edu as an **Academic Letter**.

2017 Research paper titled "Construction of Identity and

Multiculturalism in Fictional Novels: A Semiotic and Psychoanalytic study of 'The Namesake' by Jhumpa Lahiri" by Untested Ideas Research Centre, New York, in their international peer reviewed journal, viz.,

"Language and Communication Quarterly"

2017 Research paper titled "Semiotic and Psychoanalytic

analysis in the field of Communication" by IMS Unison University, Dehradun, in their peer reviewed journal viz., "Pragyaan: Journal of Mass Communication", a biannual referred journal (Listed in Ulrich's International

Periodicals Directory, USA)

#### Book:

Edition 2022 Published chapter "Post-Normal Times: Identity of

**Media in Parenthesis"** in the book titled "Credibility Crisis of the Media" by Paarth Publications with ISBN no.

978-81-954742-0-2

2021 Published book titled "After You My Soul" with

Maninanest Publications as a Co-author in July 2021

with ISBN number – 978-93-5452-222-2

**Projects:** Working on Radio project of collecting Flaneuse's observation about Mumbai as a city of Films and Dreams. (1st – 5th April, Mumbai visit)

- Organiser of *Film Festival* in April 2022 by School of Journalism & Mass Communication, Himgiri Zee University.
- Published book titled "Framing and Sense-making: Indian Cinema" 978-81-954742-4-0

# Awards/Fellowships Received:

- Awarded "Student of the Year" in 2011, MA in Communication (Doon University)
- Awarded Research Grant/ Fellowship as PhD scholar during Pre-PhD course work (Doon University, 2014-15)

# Computer/Technical Proficiency:

- Knowledge of software(s)-: SPSS, NVivo, QRD Miner (Comparable to MAXQDA), Excel
- Knowledge of software(s) like FCP, Adobe Premiere, Photoshop, Corel Draw and Quark Xpress
- Knowledge of Still and video camera Handling

# **Conferences/ Workshops / Seminars:**

Feb 2022 Industry Training – Training on Operations of

Broadcast and Media Industry, ZMCL Noida.

Jan 2022 Virtual Global Conference, ICMC 2022, organised by MICA, India, in collaboration with University of Southampton, England.

Jan 2022 Attended one week Faculty Development Program on "Bibliometric Analysis with VOS Viewers" organised by Himgiri Zee University.

July 2019 Attended one week Faculty Development Program (FDP) on "Innovative Approaches in Teaching & Learning Process" organised by Himgiri Zee University

June 2018 Attended National Workshop on "Statistical and Optimization learning in Multidisciplinary Arena" in conjunction with National Statistics Day organised by Department of Mathematics and Statistics, Manipal University, Jaipur.

Presented research paper titled "Identity Construction in Diaspora Literature: A Psychoanalytic Study of Americanah by Chimamanda Ngozi Adichie" at International Conference on "Emergence of Globalization: Towards Transnationalism" held at Osmania University, Hyderabad

Nov. 2016 Presented research paper titled "On C.S.Peirce's theory of signs: Node connecting language, communication and pragmatism" at IV International Conference "MAGIC'16 Methods, Aesthetics and Genre in Communication"- organised by Centre for Professional Communication, University of Petroleum & Energy Studies, Dehradun, Uttarakhand, India.

## Freelance Work/Internship:

Freelance work

Since 2019 Working with RAG Enterprises as product creator (Handmade items)

June 2016 Worked with Inceptions, Media Production Studio based in Dehradun as "content creator & designer" for three months.

August 2013 Worked with Incredible Travellers, Traveling Company with Head Office in New Delhi and Branch Office in Auckland, New Zealand as "content creator & designer".

Internship:

One and a half month Summer Internship at "STRIDES" Advertising Agency, New Delhi

# YouTube Channel: Online Content

https://www.youtube.com/ch annel/UCy6CN9nlOQoFwU7CY38cvg

#### LinkedIn:

https://www.linkedin.com/in/garima-singh-090a0ab6/

## **Documentary Projects:**

- Worked individually on two documentary projects -"Inspiration", and "Heard but still unheard, story of Lakhamandal"
- Worked as team member in the documentary "A Walk in Paltan"

#### Hobbies:

- Reading books and papers
- Writing Poems, blogs
- Creating handmade ecofriendly products

#### Personal Details

Date of Birth: 09/05/1988 Father's Name: Mr. Pramod

Kumar

Gender: Female Marital Status: Single

Languages Known: Hindi,

English

Nationality: Indian

# Online Courses and Workshops:

March 2022 Workshop on "Reference Management with

Mendeley" offered by Commacad.

Dec. 2021 International Web Conference on 'Contemporary

Cinema at International Film Festivals' jointly

organized by IIT Madras & C PRASIS.

August 2021 Qualitative Research with NVivo" offered by Commacad.

July 2021 "Data Analysis with SPSS" offered by Commacad.

June 2021 "Research Methodology & Thesis Writing" offered by

Commacad.

June 2020 "Introduction to Psychology: The History and Science of

Psychology" offered by Monash University (Future Learn)

May 2020 "Understanding the Mind: 15 Fascinating Psychology

Studies" offered by Audrew Luttrell via Udemy.

#### Declaration

I hereby declare that above stated information is true in best of my knowledge.

Date - 21st April, 2022

Place - Dehradun

Signature - Garima Singh